## Rebecca D. Claycamp, MS, CRA

# McKinney, TX 75072 • 301-928-4364 • claycamp-rd@gmail.com

Accomplished and creative senior research administrator with over 38 years of broad university and federal experience in research policy and compliance implementation and administration.

#### **Signature Achievements**

Transformed grants management for a large NIH institute from a paper processing unit to one directly and significantly involved in grants compliance and oversight.

Coordinated design and implementation of NIH-level tools for scientific, administrative and fiscal oversight of awards in 2006-07 and their redesign in 2015-17.

Award-winning background includes recognition as an accomplished educator and presenter on topics across the research administration spectrum from both sponsor and recipient perspectives.

### **Professional Experience**

Chief Grants Management Officer: National Institute of Mental Health 1/2003 – 3/2020; Senior Advisor (contractor): 4-11/2020

Oversee all fiscal and administrative grants activities for a \$1.6 billion annual portfolio, including over 3200 awards to 396 different recipient organizations. In directing a staff of 25, continually adjust and enhance Institute procedures to maximize success of extramural programs. A change agent representing the Institute at the NIH-level. Recipient of multiple NIMH and NIH awards. As Senior Advisor, helped to ensure smooth transition of new Chief GMO during COVID.

Notable Accomplishments:

- Mitigated risk to the NIMH by directing implementation of diverse NIH policies, including clinical trials management, data sharing and financial conflict of interest.
- Facilitated Institute leadership to creatively and effectively address issues associated with funding level changes, shifting priorities, poor optics and perpetual change.
- Routinely troubleshot problems and find responsive solutions to deal with poor grant performance, human subjects noncompliance, research misconduct and fraud, with some actions leading to direct interactions with NIH Office of General Counsel, Office of Human Research Protections, HHS Office of the Inspector General and the Department of Justice.
- Collaborated with the NIH Office of Extramural Research on projects as diverse as creation of multiple-PI and development of program and grants management award monitoring checklists. Frequent present at the NIH Regional Workshops

**Deputy Grants Management Officer:** *National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke* 8/2001 – 12/2002

**Assistant Chair:** Department of Chemistry, University of Pittsburgh 8/1990 – 6/2001

Responsible for the overall administration of a large research and instructional department. Served three chairs, including N. John Cooper (Dean of Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1998-2017) and Andrew Hamilton (current President of NYU). Frequent participant on University working committees.

#### Notable Accomplishments:

- Directed the financial and administrative management of the department's \$20 million annual budget, grant and contract oversight, facilities and human resources.
- Handled diverse staff issues impacting faculty, including conflict situations, substandard employee performance, sexual harassment, discrimination, and stalking.
- Coordinated academic administration efforts including faculty hiring support packages, department teaching assignments and graduate student recruitment and admissions.
- Spearheaded public relations efforts, including the department's first website, an alumni newsletter and a distinguished alumni award to coincide with the 125<sup>th</sup> anniversary.

**Research Development Coordinator:** Division of Sponsored Programs, University of Iowa 7/1986 – 5/1990

One of four central research administration staff overseeing the administration of \$150 million in research awards annually, including coordination of institutional applications and signoff of proposals. Responsible for grant and contract negotiation on a daily basis with the NSF, NASA, Army Medical Command, Department of Energy, private corporations and nonfederal agencies.

**International Outreach Coordinator:** Office of International Education and Services, University of Iowa 9/1985 – 6/1986

**Coordinator of Grant Development and External Affairs:** Institute of Public Policy and Business Research, University of Kansas 8/1982 – 9/1985

#### **Education and Professional Development**

M.S. in Biology (Biochemical Genetics), University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, AL

B.Sc. in Pure Zoology, University of Reading, Reading, England; transferred in from the University of Illinois

Certified Research Administrator (charter recipient); served multiple terms on the Research Administrators Certification Council (RACC) Board of Directors

Member of the Society of Research Administrators since 1986, serving in regional and national leadership roles. Distinguished Faculty member. Currently involved in microcredentialing curriculum development.